Johnson Adebayo

18, Oladiran Farodoye Street, Peace Estate, Gbagada, Lagos, Nigeria.

+2349099921571, +2347089176199

b.adejohnson@hotmail.com, mailjohnson.adebayo@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/johnson-adebayo

GitHub: https://github.com/jhonsphorus

Medium: https://medium.com/@mailjohnson.adebayo

Rpubs: https://rpubs.com/Jhonsphorus

CAREER SUMMARY

Enthusiastic data scientist/Analyst with 6+ years of experience that cut across oil and gas, education, and analytics, eager to contribute to team success through hard work, attention to detail, and excellent organizational skills. A clear understanding of cloud platforms and services, data cleaning, transformation, visualization, modeling, pipeline, and petroleum production. Motivated to learn, grow and excel in data science and analytics.

SKILLS

- Skilled in SQL and databases.
- Ability to use Google Cloud Platform services and products for data storage, analysis, etc.
- Data storage, query, and analysis with Google Bigquery.
- Ability to design and implement data pipeline for ETL with GCP products.
- Data cleaning, preparation, integration, and pipeline with Google Cloud Data Fusion and Dataprep.
- Firebase and Google Analytics for analysing, monitoring and reporting app traffic sources, revenue etc.
- Using google data studio to create reports, dashboards, and analyze data.
- Data visualization and analysis using R, Python, Excel, Google Data Studio, Looker and Power BI.
- Ability to build, score and evaluate machine learning models in R, Bigquery, and Microsoft Azure ML with machine learning algorithms (e.g., Linear regression, logistic regression, decision tree, SVM, KNN, etc.).
- Deploying and integrating the Azure machine learning model with Power BI.
- Data processing using R (dplyr, tidyr, etc.) and Python (Numpy, etc.)
- Ability to convert R code to web API using plumber package.
- Ability to create and deploy dashboards and applications using shiny package in R.

EDUCATION

The Federal University of Technology, Akure, Nigeria

B.Eng. in Mining Engineering – Second Class Upper OCTOBER 2006 – SEPTEMBER 2011

EXPERIENCE

Nevada Bridge TV, Lagos, Nigeria – Data Analyst

JULY 2021 - PRESENT

- Prepare weekly and monthly reports from multiple systems, e.g., Firebase, Google Data Studio, Google datastore, etc.
- Design and implement data pipeline for ETL using GCP.
- Gain useful insights from NBTV data to advise the top management team and make vital business decisions.
- Carry out analysis on subscriptions, subscribers, and payment data to determine daily, weekly, monthly performance etc.
- Carry out analysis on subscribers' data using Bigquery and data studio to determine weekly and monthly most-watched movies, series, and shows.
- Migrate and export data from google datastore, google drive, local storage, etc. into Google Cloud Storage.
- Export data from different sources such as Google Cloud Storage, google drive, local storage, and Bigtable into Google Bigquery for analysis and insights.
- Analyse NBTV app revenue, users' engagement, traffic sources, users' retention, active users, etc. on firebase.
- Build machine learning models using R, Vertex AI, and Bigquery to optimize the cost of cloud services and forecast NBTV spending on cloud services as the number of subscribers increase.
- Analyse NBTV app user's demographics, technology platform, in-app purchase, user acquisition, etc. on google analytics with funnel and path exploration.
- Carry out ETL (Extract, Transform, and Load) on data with google Dataprep.
- Integrate data from multiple sources and create a data pipeline with google Cloud Data Fusion.

Semicolon Africa, Lagos, Nigeria – Data Scientist

MARCH 2019 - JULY 2021

- Collected, cleaned, visualized and stored data using tools such as R, Python, Power BI, Microsoft Azure ML, and MySQL.
- Built and deployed machine learning models to the cloud using R and Microsoft Azure ML.
- Built and maintained dashboards and applications using shiny and flexdashboard (R packages).
- Carried out A/B test analysis and another hypothesis testing on product samples.
- Built models for predicting loan worthiness, medical insurance pricing, forecasting time series data such as price, sales, etc., recommendation platform using ML algorithms.
- Analysed large amounts of data to discover trends and patterns.

- Built reports, dataflow, dashboards, and apps using Power BI for data visualization and analysis.
- Applied visualization techniques to assist in decision-making.
- Collaborated with domain experts and products development teams.

Semicolon Africa, Lagos, Nigeria – Data Scientist

IPMC Project – Petroleum Reservoir Optimization using Analytics

OCTOBER 2020 - DECEMBER 2020

- I worked in a team of data analytics experts and cloud architects to optimize oil and gas
 reservoir production by analyzing and building machine learning models for petroleum
 reservoir pressure, oil, gas, and water production rate using R, Power BI, and Microsoft
 Azure ML.
- Deployed the models to the cloud using Microsoft Azure ML web service.

Factual Analytics, Lagos, Nigeria - Data Analyst

OCTOBER 2017 - MARCH 2019

- Acquired and loaded dataset using packages in R and Python.
- Cleaned, manipulated, and transformed datasets using dplyr, tidyr, etc.
- Visualized data to determine trends and patterns in data using ggplot (package in R), Power BI, and matplotlib (library in Python).
- Analysed and interpreted data.
- Created models to gain useful insights into data and make informative decisions.
- Created dashboards and reports with clear visualization.

Narag Energy Solutions Limited, Lagos, Nig. - Field Production Engineer

APRIL 2015 - JULY 2017

- Managed and handled oil and gas production optimization projects.
- Continuously audit client existing production data.
- Liaised with customers Field Operations Managers and Production Superintendents.
- Gained hands-on Production engineering experience working on Technical Sales production optimization products, Reservoir Engineering solutions, and production Optimization projects, ranging from field support to possible field visits.
- Trained client's field production Operators on how to operate SCADA systems.

Platform Petroleum Limited, Lagos, Nig. – Production Operations Engineer

DEC 2011 - JUNE 2013

- Collected and analyzed crude oil samples from wellheads and manifold to determine their BS&W, API Gravity, and Specific Gravity.
- Reconciliation of crude oil sharing with the Joint Venture partner.
- Controlled and monitored process operations through the DCS/SCADA system.

- Prepared and compiled weekly and monthly production activities and forward them to the Production Supervisor.
- Monitored, and collected data and QA/QC of the crude oil from the export line.
- Assisted in the facilitation of daily production meetings with HSE, Production facility Operations, Maintenance, Technical Services, Well Surface and subsurface Engineering, etc.

SOFTWARE

Data Science and Analytics: R (R Studio), Python, Azure ML, Power BI, Google Analytics

Big Data: Google Bigquery, Google Cloud Storage, Google Datastore

Data Pipeline: Data Fusion, Dataprep, Dataflow

Data Warehouse: Google Bigquery

Cloud Platform: Google Cloud Platform, Microsoft Azure

Data Visualization Tools/Packages: Power BI, ggplot, matplotlib, Data Studio, Looker

Database/SQL: MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server, Google BigQuery, Google Cloud SQL

API Generator: Plumber (R package for generating web API), Azure ML

Programming Framework(s): Django, Shiny (R web framework)

Source Control: Git (GitHub)

Oil and Gas Software: ECLIPSE, Petrel RE, PROSPER

Work and Project Management: Proteus OS

CERTIFICATIONS AND PROFESSIONAL TRAINING

Google Cloud Training	Google Cloud Big Data and	2021
	Machine Learning Fundamental	
Google Cloud Training	Modernizing Data Lakes and Data	2021
	Warehouses with Google Cloud	
Google Cloud Training	From Data to Insights with	2021
	Google Cloud	
Google Cloud Training	Applying Machine Learning	2021
	to your Data with GCP	
Google Cloud Training	Creating New BigQuery Datasets	2021
	and Visualizing Insights	
Google Cloud Training	Exploring and Preparing your Data	2021
	With BigQuery	
Google Cloud Training	Achieving Advance Insights	2021
	With BigQuery	
Google Cloud Training	BigQuery Basics for Data	2021
	Analyst	
Semicolon Africa	Software Engineering	2019 - 2020
IBM (Cognitive Class)	Data Visualization with R	2020

IBM (Cognitive Class)	Data Analysis with Python	2020
Data Science Nigeria	Introduction to Machine	2020
	Learning	

IBM (Cognitive Class) Python for Data Science 2019

ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Led a multi-disciplinary team of software and analytics professionals to develop a platform for loan risk analysis.
- Headed a multidisciplinary team to build a voting and streaming platform for Naija Hood Rep 2022 (an NBTV reality show).
- Built a machine learning model to optimize the cloud service cost considering the number of subscribers and other factors as inputs.
- Increase in the number of subscribers from the insights gained in the subscriber data, payment data, viewers data, etc.
- Developed interactive dashboard for analyzing and forecasting time series data such as company sales data, production data, price of oil, etc.
- Built predictive petroleum reservoir pressure and oil production model to optimize oil and gas fields.

AFFILIATIONS

- Member, Lagos R User Group (RUG)
- Member, Data Science Nigeria (DSN/AIPlus/2019/0320)
- Member, Society of Petroleum Engineers (#4804090)

PROJECTS PORTFOLIO

- **InsurrApp** Insurance pricing platform for predicting medical insurance costs. https://phorus2.shinyapps.io/InsurrApp/
- Afriloan An application for predicting the loan worthiness of applicants. <u>https://phorus.shinyapps.io/Afriloan2/</u>
- **TSForecastApp** An application for forecasting time series datasets such as sales, production, etc.
 - https://ihonsphorus.shinyapps.io/timeseries app/
- **PhorusRecommender** A recommendation engine that suggests movies to users based on their selections and ratings.
 - https://phorus2.shinyapps.io/PhorusRecommender1/
- NigeriaTelecomDashboard A web application built with shiny for analyzing Nigeria's Telecommunication Industry data.
 - https://phorus.shinyapps.io/NigeriaTelecomDashboard/